Dr. Jiajian Xiao

Email: jiajian.xiao@outlook.com | Mobile: +65 8381 8875

INTRO

I am currently working as a Senior Scientist II at Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A*STAR) Singapore. My research interests span high-performance computing, focusing on deploying applications on heterogeneous hardware, agent-based simulation, and intelligent transportation. I am one of the core architects and developers of a microscopic agent-based mobility simulator – <u>CityMoS</u>. I have been involved in and led a number of research projects, collaborating with research entities and industrial partners in Singapore, Germany, Austria, and China.

EXPERIENCE

 $Scientist~(Mar~2023-Jun~2023) \rightarrow Senior~Scientist~II~(Jul~2023-present)$

Mar 2023 – present

Location: Singapore

A*STAR, Institute of High Performance Computing

Singapore

• Working with government agencies and industrial partners on various scientific challenges, utilizing machine learning and simulation approaches.

Research Fellow Sep 2020 – Mar 2023

TUMCREATE (A research center founded by National Research Foundation Singapore)

Singapore

- Co-led the simulation efforts on the TUMCREATE side for the Singapore Integrated Transport Energy Model (SITEM) project, collaborating with A*STAR. The project's goal was to build a simulation-based digital twin solution for the decision-makers to conduct comprehensive analyses of the future electric vehicle adoption in Singapore.
- Key R&D member of the joint simulation laboratory with HUAWEI Research Centre Munich Mobility in Virtual Environments at Scale (MoVES) Lab.

Research Associate
TUMCREATE
Apr 2016 – Aug 2020
Singapore

- Daily tasks involved both engineering and research work. Engineering work included software development (in C++) of the CityMoS simulator. Research work focused on accelerating agent-based simulations using emerging hardware.
- Built a general compiler framework to automate the acceleration of agent-based simulations on heterogeneous hardware (a mixed hardware setting with CPUs, GPUs, FPGAs, etc.)

Software Developer
TUMCREATE
Mar 2014 – Mar 2016
Singapore

• One of the main C++ backend and frontend developers of a microscopic agent-based traffic simulator – CityMoS.

EDUCATION

Technical University of Munich (Supervisor: Prof. Alois Knoll)

Munich, G

Munich, Germany/Singapore

Doctor (Co-supervised by Prof. Wentong Cai from Nanyang Technological University)

Apr 2016 - Oct 2022

Technical University of Munich *Master of Science in Computer Science*

Munich, Germany Oct 2011 – Dec 2013

Musici of Science in Comparer Science

Shanghai, China

Shanghai Jiao Tong University

Sep 2007 - Jul 2011

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages : C/C++, Objective-C, CUDA, OpenCL, ARM/Intel Assembly, Java, JavaScript, HTML, CSS

Frameworks : Express, Node.js, Redis, ZeroMQ, MPI, OpenMP, LLVM/Clang

Databases : Oracle SQL, MongoDB, PostgreSQL

Tools & OSs : Docker, Adobe Photoshop/Premiere, Windows, Linux, macOS

Honors

FireFly Silver Borderless Award Ministry of Trade and Industry Singapore

Best Paper Award
IEEE/ACM DS-RT 2018

Singapore Jun~2022

Spain Oct 2018

SELECTED HIGH-IMPACT PUBLICATIONS

Full list on Google Scholar

- A survey on agent-based simulation using hardware accelerators. Xiao, J., Andelfinger, P., Eckhoff, D., Cai, W. and Knoll, A., 2019. ACM Computing Surveys (CSUR), 51(6) (IF: 14.324, top computer science journal)
- Exploring execution schemes for agent-based traffic simulation on heterogeneous hardware. Xiao, J., Andelfinger, P., Eckhoff, D., Cai, W., & Knoll, A.; In 2018 IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Distributed Simulation and Real-Time Applications (Best Paper Award)
- A Partition-Based Match Making Algorithm for Dynamic Ridesharing. Pelzer, D., Xiao, J., Zehe, D., Lees, M.H., Knoll, A.C., Aydt, H.; 2015. IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems (IF 9.551, top transportation journal)
- Pedal to the Bare Metal: Road Traffic Simulation on FPGAs Using High-Level Synthesis. Xiao, J., Kilinç, G., Andelfinger, P., Eckhoff, D., Cai, W., & Knoll, A. In Proceedings of the 2020 ACM SIGSIM Conference on Principles of Advanced Discrete Simulation (1st known effort for agent-based traffic simulations using HLS)
- OpenABLext: An automatic code generation framework for agent-based simulations on CPU-GPU-FPGA heterogeneous platforms. Xiao, J., Andelfinger, P., Cai, W., Richmond, P., Knoll, A., & Eckhoff, D. 2020. Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, e5807
- OptCL: A Middleware to Optimise Performance for High-Performance Domain-Specific Languages on Heterogeneous Platforms. Xiao, J., Andelfinger, P., Cai, W., Eckhoff, D., & Knoll, A. In 2021 International Conference on Algorithms and Architectures for Parallel Processing (A middleware accelerates not only agent-based simulation but also general arithmetic e.g., machine learning algorithms)